<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands weeping spectacle: or, The sad condition of Lievtenant Colonell John Lilburne : crying to all who have any conscience or compassion, for assistance and deliverance from his unjust, long and cruell sufferings. Wherein (as in a glasse) all Englishmen may see the slavish condition, unto which (after so much blood, time and treasure spent) they are yet by perfidious men (who vowed and promised to deliver them from all tyrannie and oppression) still most wofully subjected.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E450_7</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864562</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161896</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88183)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161896)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E450[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands weeping spectacle: or, The sad condition of Lievtenant Colonell John Lilburne : crying to all who have any conscience or compassion, for assistance and deliverance from his unjust, long and cruell sufferings. Wherein (as in a glasse) all Englishmen may see the slavish condition, unto which (after so much blood, time and treasure spent) they are yet by perfidious men (who vowed and promised to deliver them from all tyrannie and oppression) still most wofully subjected.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Yeere 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Lilburne; cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to William Walwyn; this attribution rejected by McMichael and Taft, The writings of William Walwyn, pp.530-1.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161896:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS weeping ſpectacle: OR, The ſad condition of Lievtenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>John Lilburne:</hi> Crying to all who have any conſcience or compaſſion, for aſſiſtance and deliverance from his unjuſt, long and cruell ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Wherein (as in a glaſſe) all Engliſhmen may ſee the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh condition, unto which (after ſo much blood, time and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſpent) they are yet by perfidious men (who vowed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to deliver them from all tyrannie and oppreſſion) ſtill moſt wofully ſubjected.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 11.26. Matth. 26.44, 45, 46.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The righteouſneſſe of the upright ſhall deliver them, but tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors ſhall be taken in their own wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall they alſo anſwer him, ſaying, when ſaw we thee an hungry, or athirſt, or a ſtranger, or naked, or ſick or in priſon, and did not miniſter unto thee?</p>
               <p>Then ſhall he anſwer them, and ſay, verily I ſay unto you, in as much as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me.</p>
               <p>And theſe ſhall go into everlaſting paine, and the righteous unto life etenrall.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161896:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161896:2"/>
            <head>Englands weeping Spectacle, or the ſad condition of Lievtenant-Colonell <hi>JOHN LILBURNE;</hi> Crying to all who have any conſcience or compaſſion, for aſſiſtance and deliverance from his unjuſt, long and cruell ſufferings.</head>
            <p>CErtainly in it ſelfe, and to a ſound and vertuous mind, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo ſad, ſo irkſome and grievous, as the unjuſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of an honeſt and faithfull man, who for his hatred to oppreſſion, and love to the juſt Liberty of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, is made a prey to Tyrants, and the ſubject of their ſcorn, pride, and malice.</p>
            <p>And if this be ſo, as it muſt needs be, <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifying, <hi>that for a good man ſome would even dare to die,</hi> thereby ſignifying his exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive griefe, (when vertue and goodneſſe ſuffers) and in this reſpect, who can forbeare to weep, that conſiders the long and cruell ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of M. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> which were not for any unjuſt action, nor for obtaining ſome particular good to himſelfe, but in the conſtant purſuance of the generall good of this long-betrayed and inſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Nation.</p>
            <p>When firſt he began to underſtand himſelf, had he been like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to moſt young men of his age and time, who either waſt their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities on vaine fantaſtick pleaſures, or hunt after the ſordid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of ambition and covetouſneſſe, minding little elſe but the pride, vanity, and luxury of a ſinfull life, mixt at beſt, only with a forme of Godlineſſe, without the power or life thereof, no doubt but he might ſoone have come to have been a man of this world, to have been ſome body in the City and place where he was bred; and have enjoyed thoſe contents, which moſt men ſeeke either in honour or profit.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems his conſcience was ſoon awakened upon his Maſters call, God to whoſe ſervice he had dedicated himſelf, made him to know betimes, that he had other work for him to doe, and being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161896:3"/>called, he neither ſuffered the motions of God in his conſcience to be choaked with the cares of this world, nor the deceitfulneſſe of riches, nor conſult with fleſh and blood, but (as <hi>Moſes</hi>) he chuſed rather to ſuffer affliction in purſuance of a juſt cauſe, then to injoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Hereupon, he finding all Authority corrupted and perverted from the true end, (the preſervation and freedome of the people) to its contrary, the ruine, vexation, and bondage of the people: his conſcience preſently ſets him awork, waving all ſelfe-reſpects to the diſcovery thereof, by printing and publiſhing of bookes whereby to open the underſtandings of men, and ſtirring them up to a timely prevention of that intolerable bondage, which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be coming faſt upon them.</p>
            <p>Whilſt he was thus employed, the Lordly Biſhops and corrupt States-men (whoſe wickedneſſe was laid open through his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours) did by the craft of their officious inſtruments and trechery of fained friends, lay hold of him, and proceed againſt him in Star-Chamber, where after moſt corrupt proceedings, he is put to that vile Oath <hi>Ex Officio,</hi> enjoyning him to anſwer to all ſuch queſtions as they ſhould demand, even to Articles againſt himſelfe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to nature, reaſon, Law and Religion, he abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to anſwer, inſiſts upon his right, and declares the illegality and abominable wickedneſſe of ſuch proceedings.</p>
            <p>For refuſing whereof, they ſentence him to be whipt at a Cart, from the Fleet-priſon, to Weſtminſter-hall, and there to be ſet on the Pillory for many houres, to be a wonder to all men, and with what malice this cruelty was executed, how bloodily he was whipt, how cruelly gagg'd, and after that, how barbarouſly he was uſed in his impriſonment in the Fleet, would be no leſſe ſad, then tedious to rehearſe, yea and is of it ſelfe ſufficient, had his ſufferings ended there, even to make every true-hearted Engliſh-man, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremy, to wiſh that his head were a well of water, and his eyes fountaines of tears, that he might weep day and night,</hi> that any govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pretending Chriſtianity ſhould be ſo inhumane, or any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple profeſſing the knowledge of God, or common equity, ſhould be ſo ſottiſh as to ſtand by, obſerve and ſuffer ſuch inhumane cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, whereof the particulars have been ſo fully and frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, that it is needleſſe here to repeat them; theſe are times wherein Chriſtians are not Children in knowledge, but rather in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161896:3"/>conſcience and practice, or elſe this <hi>weeping Spectacle</hi> would make their heats to bleed, and burne within them, till they had found out ſome way of deliverance for him.</p>
            <p>But did his ſorrowes end here? No; but as the injuſtice and cruelty of his adverſaries abated not his courage, (as they ſuppoſed and expected) but rather increaſed and heightned his reſolution, according to the nature of true Chriſtian fortitude, ſo hath the ſame ever ſince, moved him with undaunted courage, to ſtand in oppoſition to the oppreſſion and injuſtice of the times, and by that meanes begotten him more and greater affliction, even principally from the Parliament it ſelfe, who pretended not onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <hi>him,</hi> but all England out of all kind of bondage, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
            <p>It's confeſt, they began well, like true Chriſtians indeed, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering the captive, and ſetting the oppreſſed free, whereof he was one, and it was well for them he was ſo, for he was no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull one, but immediately (occaſion ſo requiring) ventured his life for their preſervation, againſt <hi>Lunsford</hi> and his crue of Ruffians at Weſtminſter, where the Parliament of England that had preſerved him, was by his ſpeciall meanes (under God) preſerved; the greateſt number that were there, even Sir <hi>Richard Wiſeman,</hi> himſelf, being there by his incitement, who notwithſtanding is ſince too much forgotten, and where this our weeping Spectacle was then a bleeding Spectacle to all beholders, and for which and much more both before and ſince, all true lovers of Englands Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, are beholding to him: and had not things then as well as ſince, been done by halves and deceitfully, our troubles had then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or at leaſt not halfe ſo long indured.</p>
            <p>And how ſenſible did the Parliament then ſeem to be of his ſufferings and ſervice? What could be deſired, that was not then voted in his behalfe, whether in condemnation of his tyrannous adverſaries, or in juſtification and reparation of his ſufferings and loſſes, even as far, and as faire, as the wits of men could deviſe, which is evident by their Votes then manifeſted? And this at that time gained them abundance of friends, for he was exceedingly beloved and pitied throughout the Land: Oh that all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſince had been agreeable to this, he is not a changer with the times, though they in their actions be much changed: For it had not then appeared, that this they did to him, was not for ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161896:4"/>ſake, but rather to advance a party whereby to compaſſe their owne ends, and not the publike good.</p>
            <p>But ſo really thankfull is this good man, for their ſeeming good to him, and to the publike in him, (for he and the publike are but one, as time will prove effectually) that no ſooner did their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities declare for VVarre, but he ingages himſelfe, and all the friends he had, one way or other to ingage for them, and for their ſakes, (ſuppoſing then they minded really the Commons Liberties, and the redreſſe of all grievances) forſakes his calling wherein he lived comfortably, and leaves his wife, dearer to him then himſelfe, as ſhe well deſerved, honouring and comforting him before ſhe was ſo, even when he was more like <hi>Job</hi> upon the dunghill by his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, then a man at that time for her ſociety: And at Kenton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field ventured his life freely for them, and his Countrey, ſo that he gained very much reſpect from all who obſerved his faithfulneſſe and valour.</p>
            <p>Nor does he deſiſt here, though by what he had ſeen both at Worceſter and at this fight, he had cauſe to doubt, that there was no intention of a ſpeedy end to the war, or of liberty to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but occaſion at Branford againe requiring his ſervice, he there for many houres with an inconſiderable party of men that can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be too much honoured, holds all the Enemies Forces at a bay, and inforces them to a ſtand till London was provided, which otherwiſe in probability had ben ſurprized on a ſudden, and where he loſt himſelfe to redeem his Countrey, being in a worſe condition then thoſe many worthy men there ſlaine; for he was led in a moſt deſpicable manner from thence to Oxford, where he underwent a long and loathſome impriſonment, with moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous uſage from <hi>Smith</hi> the cruell Jaylor, and a moſt dangerous tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for his life before Judge <hi>Heath:</hi> and though he daily expected certaine death, yet ſtood he firme againſt all kinds of temptations and promiſes, whether of honour, or profit, or deliverance from his preſent miſery, firme as built upon a Rock, even the Rock Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and a cauſe (as his conſcience had digeſted it) juſt as juſtice it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And for defence whereof, he had certainly and ſuddenly died the moſt ſhamefull death, if the faithfulneſſe of his wife had not even in the very inſtant prevented the judgement and execution, for ſhe knowing his danger, ceaſed not to ſolicite the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161896:4"/>daily and hourely to interpoſe their power for his preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and when by ordinary ſolicitation ſhe could not prevaile, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſo much inforcing, ſhe took the boldneſſe to preſent her ſelf at the Commons Barre, there begging and importuning their care of her husbands life, and was (by divine providence) ſo happy as to obtaine their Order and Letter to Judge <hi>Heath,</hi> requiring a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of his execution, and withall, threatning the death of two of their friends (being then priſoners here) in caſe they took his life.</p>
            <p>With which letter (big with child as ſhe was) ſhe undergoes a task through all the ſtrong Courts of Guard, which none elſe (as things then ſtood) durſt undertake; in performance whereof, ſhe met with ſo many ſad and difficult accidents, to a woman in her condition, as would force tears from the hardeſt heart, to heare them related, but they are too large for this place, though thoſe that know them, cannot but remember them to her perpetuall commendation, who by wiſdome, patience and diligence overcame them all, and for her reward both ſaved her husbands life, and after a ſeaſon obtained his liberty.</p>
            <p>Neither was he wearied by theſe his ſufferings, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull for the reſpects ſhewed unto him by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as witneſſe his ſpeedy ingagement under the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> in which ſervice it is well knowne, he was ſo faithfull, reſolute, and ſucceſſefull, that he became the darling and boſome-friend to the now Lievtenant-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> through whoſe unhappy intimacy he had ſo great an inſpection into the actions of the Earle himſelfe, and likewiſe of Col. <hi>King,</hi> that when <hi>Cromwell</hi> impeached the ſaid Earle upon many dangerous articles, he had not ſo materiall a witneſſe (or that durſt ſo effectually appeare) as his truſty friend Lievetenant-Colonell <hi>Lilburne,</hi> who (not knowing what belonged to fear or diſtruſt) boldly diſcovers upon examination, all that he knew or could te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, and which made up ſo much as the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, upon report of the Committee, voted the charge to be fully proved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:161896:5"/>But here endeth the charge, (to Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> and all true hearted Engliſh mens great griefe, which otherwiſe if it had been proſecuted, might then have made an end of all theſe warres, troubles and oppreſſions) and here began Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> and all other honeſt mens overthrow, by meanes of thoſe deceitfull inſtruments unto this day:</p>
            <p>For inſtantly upon this ceſſation and alteration, diverſe unworthy officious men were ſet awork both upon him and all that loved him and his cauſe, even by printed, rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; lying pamphlets, to abuſe, vex and provoke him, unto which he anſwering &amp; replying in way of juſtifying himſelf and his friends, is haſtily complained on to the Parliament, his perſon ſummoned by Warrants from the Committee of Examinations, where (as before in Starchamber) he is demanded queſtions againſt himſelfe, which he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to anſwer, they make no longer debate, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſend him to Newgate, purpoſely to diſparage and provoke him more and more, wherein Mr. <hi>Miles Corbet</hi> and Mr. <hi>VVhitaker</hi> were very forward.</p>
            <p>And though they had no Commiſſion ſo to doe, yet the houſe of Commons, both juſtifies the Committee, and directs the Recorder of London, to prepare for his tryall at Seſſions for his life, as if there had been ſome capitall crime or dangerous matter againſt him, and in this baſe priſon he lyeth almoſt three months, and of what ſlaunders were reported and Plots diviſed againſt him, all this time not onely his and his friends ſad experience at preſent, but the accuſing conſcience of his enemies will in due time bear witneſſe: And then upon his owne motion to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Seſſions, and upon their hearing him in open Court by a publick ſpeech (defying all his accuſers and all their accuſations) was by proclamation ſet free, without any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall crime layed to his charge, either by Parliament or any other; whereby he gained the more credit and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, &amp; all his enemies the more ſhame &amp; contempt ever ſince.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161896:5"/>Well, all this he puts up (there being no way of remedy yet found our, for any injuſtice of the Houſe of Commons, nor of their Committees) and imployes his induſtry to get his due arreares, &amp; the dammages Voted him formerly for his cruell ſufferings in the Starre-Chamber, and having with continuall paines early and late, at length prevailed ſo farre, as that the Houſe of Lords aſſigned him two thouſand pounds, upon due triall and proofe of the buſineſſe, and he being in good hopes of a ſpeedy iſſue, Col. <hi>King</hi> is put upon him to bring him to further troubles, and fruſtrat all his endeavours, and for a beginning arreſts him upon an action for Slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous words, which he pretended to be ſpoken againſt him, whereas the words indeed were in way of proving <hi>King</hi> an offender, upon Articles exhibited againſt him in Parliament, and <hi>King aid this purpoſely to take away his Teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you are to minde, that Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> had left the ſervice of the Warres, upon a juſt diſlike of the corrupt managing thereof, and being here about <hi>London,</hi> had diſcovered the perverſe proceeding of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; now hateful all ſorts of conſcientious people (whatever they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly pretended) were unto them; and thereupon invited others, and joyned with them by Petitions to induce them to a better temper. And this his forwardneſſe for publick good, occaſioned all men who had any publick greevances to diſcover, to come to him and to aske his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which brought ſome trouble, and more feare upon diverſe that yet bear their heads full high, and wrought him more enmity, then that either of the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> or of Colonel <hi>King,</hi> for all that had any guilt upon them new or old were greatly affraid of him; ſo that <hi>King</hi> gained aboundance of friends, as <hi>Prynne</hi> and <hi>Baſtwicke</hi> had done before, by thus abuſing Mr. <hi>Lilburne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But being arreſted by <hi>King</hi> in the Court of Common Pleas, and put to his defence, having in all this time received no part of his dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, nor but a hundred Pounds of all his arreares, (which was ſpent (in theſe his ſufferings) before he had it) and finding the preceedings in law, full of intricacy and perplexity both irrationall and deſtructive to himſelfe and the people, he thence takes occaſion to Petition the Houſe of Commons, that the Charge and Articles againſt King might be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Counſell of Warre, before King ſhould be permitted to proceed againſt him; this Petition he could never get to be delivered, or read in the Houſe; then after long and tedious attendance, to ſave himſelfe, and for the good of the people, (who are ever one) hee writes a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Judge <hi>Reeves,</hi> and Prints it, and calls it, <hi>The juſt mans juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:161896:6"/>wherein he layes open the great corruption and unreaſonableneſſe of the Lawes and proceedings therein, which are now yet in force (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this long laſting Parliament) and intreats him to lay thoſe things to heart, and in due ſenſe thereof, that hee would endeavour to free, not onely him, but all the people from ſo great and grievous a bondage which was brought into this Nation, at the will and pleaſure of the <hi>Norman conquerour,</hi> by force and violence of the Sword, or to this effect was the ſcope, tenor, and end of his Letter.</p>
            <p>The unjuſt Judge finding that this booke tended maynly to diſcover the jugling of Judges and Lawyers, to ſpoile their Trade and Myſterie of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quity, whereby they both heap up riches, and in effect ſway the whole Nation inſtead of doing what a good Conſcience would have bound him to, he (like himſelfe) by way of complaint, preſents the book to the Houſe of Lords, where not only <hi>Moncheſter</hi> his deadlyeſt enemy is Speaker, but ſome of thoſe wicked m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n alſo, who ſentenced Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> in the Starre-Chamber, are now again his Judges, with the reſt, againſt whoſe legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power and jurisdiction over Commoners, he is generally known to be a juſt and profeſt oppoſite.</p>
            <p>And is he not here now in a ſad condition, ſummoned he is before theſe Lords, and boldly appears; is he not where all the Judges, Lawyers Oppreſſors, Projectors, and Committeemen could wiſh him? Is it not now come to paſſe as King would have it? For the Lords very well know whom they have before them, &amp; how to handle him, they firſt (trading the ordinary path of Tyrants) put him to anſwer to queſtions againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe concerning the book, he in ſhort, diſclaimes their jurisdiction over him, and preſents to them his appeale to the Commons as a Commoners for which they judge him to be worthy of no better place then Newgate, where he continued ten dayes, and was ſent for againe, and then for refuſing to kpeele before them, they returne him again to <hi>Newgate,</hi> to be kept cloſe Priſoner without Pen, Inke, and Paper, and none to have acceſſe to him, <hi>but onely his Keeper, during their pleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all thoſe things are better knowne then conſidered, and how hee after this refuſed (till he was forced) to come any more before them, and being forced, what his behaviour was, how hee refuſed againe to kneele, and how he ſtopt his eares againſt their Articles, as utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing their Authority over him, and how for this, he was ſentenced Two thouſand pound to the King, and ſeven yeares impriſonment in the <hi>Tower,</hi> where hee continued without hope of deliverance, untill the Army pretended to inſiſt for the generall Liberty and Freedome of the Nation, as well from the new contracted, as from the old inveterate bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:161896:6"/>In all which time, it is not unknown how diligent he was, to make the Houſe of Commons ſenſible of the unjuſtice done unto him, and to all the people of England in him, but all in vain, their long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance having changed their intereſt from that of the peoples, to this of the Lords; ſo that in effect they joyned (hand in hand) with them in oppreſſing him; which unjuſt dealing alſo, as he had done other mens before, he ſpares neither paines nor charges to publiſh to the world; whereby at length not onely the people did gain ſo much underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the honeſt ſouldiers of the Army began to be ſenſible, that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and oppreſſion was come to a height, as well in the Parliament, as in the King, and therefore could ſee no reaſon, but the ſame ought to be reſiſted in them, as it was in him.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, as for other things, ſo in particular for deliverance of him, or to procure him a legall triall, the whole Army begin to inſiſt, and whileſt they were in motion from Newmarket towards London, how many and great reſpects were manifeſted by them to him, is not unknown to thouſands, nor was it ever imagined that he ſhould have remained priſoner in the Tower, when once the Army were Maſters of it.</p>
            <p>But it clearly appeares, the greateſt number that really thought ſo were much miſtaken; for the great ones of the Army, what ever they pretended, are of nearer relation, and more ſtrongly contracted to the Lords and great ones of the Nation, then to the Commons or ſuch faithfull patriots as Mr. <hi>Lilburn;</hi> which being diſcerned by him ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then by other men, and that their practiſes tended not to a common good, he ſpares neither paines, coſt nor hazard, forthwith to diſcover their deluſion (as well as he had done other mens formerly) to the world, and finding his old friend <hi>Cromwell,</hi> to have been a chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in deſtroying the ends of their engagement, he neither flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters nor ſpares him nor any other, but layes all their actions naked to the view of the world, fore-ſhewing that which ſince is come to paſſe, and which now every man ſees and many feels, though then few or none would believe. Yet through the policie of thoſe arch-deceivers, <hi>Cromwel, Ireton,</hi> and their apoſtate inſtruments, in ſtead of amending their faults, turn this his honeſt, plain and impartiall dealing, to his ruine; for they poſſeſſed all his lovers and friends in City, Country and Army, that the man was frantick, little better then one at Bedlam, that he really drives on the Kings deſigne, and to others, upon whom ſuch ſpeeches could not work, they give out, that he was a raſh incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161896:7"/>man, and that nothing would ſatisfie him, but onely to bring all this Nation to Anarchy and confuſion.</p>
            <p>By all which their ſubtle workings, they blinded the eyes of thoſe that had them in admiration for their ſpecious ſhewes of devotion and Religion, under which veil they deceived moſt men, and ſecurely went through with deſtroying the ends of the Armies engagements, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, remonſtrances, yea vowes and proteſtations to God and man, and whereby they have made the moſt honeſt and well meaning Army that ever was in the world, and the moſt valiant, beſt beloved and moſt hopefull of all the people, to be accounted the greateſt deceiver and oppreſſor, and ſo the greateſt object of all ſcorn, contempt, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred.</p>
            <p>And this the Army and all good people got, by believing thoſe great mens falſe reports and unjuſt cenſures of Mr. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> and exchanging his faithfull and timely advices for their deluſions, and as this brought extream evill upon all honeſt men, ſo eſpecially upon him, for thoſe men having thus by their Arts and ſophiſtry overcome his reputation, they by ſlanders and reproaches in all places, ſo alienated the hearts of thoſe who formerly had comforted him in his ſufferings, and ſupported his neceſſities, that himſelf his wife and children, have been many times ſince in ſuch eatremities as is incredible to all, except thoſe onely who know how vile their ſlanderous reproaches had made him in the eyes of moſt men.</p>
            <p>And when (notwithſtanding all their malice) by his invincible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, he had lately procured ſo much liberty, as to follow his own buſineſſe, and ſometimes to go out of his priſon, how ſoon did they pick occaſion, in ſtead of being priſoner to the Lords (from which he might juſtly and rationally expect to be delivered ſpeedily by the Commons) to make him the priſoner of the Commons; and for what cauſe, even for promoting a petition for the univerſall good of the whole nation as any honeſt man will eaſily diſcern at the firſt reading thereof; yea ſuch a petition, as unto which whoſoever is an enemy, is not, nor cannot be Englands friend.</p>
            <p>Being thus a priſoner again, and hereby loſing more friends (as who that ſuffers, and hath neceſſities are not ſubject unto) doth he now faint and ſink under this addition of weight and ſorrow to his former affliction? No, he ceaſes not day and night, to make this injuſtice and cruelty known to the deceived world, ſtill writes, prints, and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes both his own juſt cauſe, and their malicious and cruell dealings,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161896:7"/>ſo plainly, ſo powerfully, and couragiouſly, that ſome who formerly had been his enemies, now are ſo farre convinced of his integrity, that they both love and honour him, to the ſhame of his backſliding friends, and are by his faithfull councel preſerved from a ſnare, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly layd for their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Certainly, if any man in the world, hath the unvaluable comfort of an impartiall, publict, active, ſincere, perſevering Conſcience, this man hath, and yet of all men in this Nation, whether under the former or preſent Government, is not this he that is deſigned to live perpetually in priſon? For what way poſſible is there for his enlargement? when the <hi>King, Biſhops, Privie Councel, Starr-chamber,</hi> and <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> ruled all, then who more then he was judged worthy of whips, torture, impriſonment, and death?</p>
            <p>Thoſe Lords that firſt pretended to ſtand for the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the people, judge him moſt worthy of bonds, and the Houſe of Commons who pretended more good to the people, then ever their prediceſſors did, yea, and both of them were preſerved by his meanes (under God) in their greateſt danger, and had feweſt to take their parts, yet it plainly here appeareth, that never any one man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more hurt from them, more palpable wrong then he hath.</p>
            <p>The preſent Clergyman that thruſt out the former, even for their cruel perſecuting of him, and ſuch as he is, do not afford him ſo much as one good word; nay, they raile on him, and perſecute no man more; thoſe Lawyers that formerly ſuffered in oppoſition to ſome kinds of oppreſſion, having forſaken their firſt love, and with <hi>Demas</hi> embraced the honours and profits of theſe times, make ſport at his ſufferings, and uſe their utmoſt power to continue, heighten, and increaſe them.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Judges that ſit in place of ſuch as were removed for Injuſtice, and who are bound by Oath, Law, and Conſcience, either to ſee him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, or brought to a legall Tryall, by 12. ſworne men of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, by whomſoever he is impriſoned, yet ſeeme to think it neither perjurie in themſelves, injuſtice to him, nor robbery to the people, to deny him this, which was never denyed to the verieſt Villaine, Rogue, Malefactor, Thiefe, or Traytor, in Newgate, and which ſince this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament began, was granted to <hi>Maquier,</hi> and <hi>Machmahoone</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, which he hath ſet forth at large, (in his book called <hi>the Law-Funerall</hi>) to the eternall infamy of thoſe Parliamentary Judges.</p>
            <p>And this hath been his portion, for no other thing, but for being the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161896:8"/>moſt conſtant, vigorous, unwearied friend to <hi>Englands</hi> liberty, and the deadlieſt enemy to its bondage and ſlavery of any man whatſoever? Nor will any perſon, Authority, or State ever prove a true friend to this Nation, that continues an Enemy to him, or otherwiſe then Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and Oppreſſors, that ſtill domineere and tyrannize over him, as their Predeceſſours in oppreſſion, the Biſhops, and Starr-Chamber-men did before them.</p>
            <p>He is thy true touchſtone, O <hi>England,</hi> thou needeſt no other to try either thy Gold or droſſe, though any man appeare or gliſter never ſo faire, if ſuch a one but ſpeake againſt him, or inſiſt onely on ſome harſh (and yet true) expreſſions in his Books, or any naturall infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as is the manner of thoſe hypocrites that doe him moſt miſchief, thou maiſt certainely reſolve upon it, that that man (whoſoever hee be) doth thereby ſhew himſelf but a counterfeit, and is not to be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the day of thy neceſſity: Inſtance but one (if thou canſt, O thou officious flatterer, who hath ſtood firme for <hi>Englands</hi> true freedome, that hath deſpiſed him: thy Patrone <hi>Cromwell</hi> himſelfe ſtumbling at this ſtone, he is fallen like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> yea, and all that ſteere his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteedy courſe, doe they not ſtagger and reele up and downe like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny drunken men, and finde no certain path wherein to walke, or ſet their feet, ſince they forſooke the ſtreight way of this juſt and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all man, Mr. <hi>Lilburne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O <hi>England,</hi> (or rather thou true part of <hi>England,</hi> that knoweſt beſt what juſt freedome is) when thou wouldeſt know whether thou art bond or free, whether thoſe thou truſteſt with thy freedome, power, and authority, deale well or ill with thee, or whether they be juſt, or unjuſt, thou needeſt not runne to the King nor Parliament, neither to the Houſe of the Kings Lords, nor to Houſe of the Peoples Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, neither enquire of thy Lawyers, nor of thy Prieſts or Judges, but look onely on him, conſider his juſt cauſe, peruſe his Writings, and deferre not to give judgement, that they are altogether become abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and reprobate to every good work, that there is none of them that doth good, no not one, their throat is an open Sepulchre, not only in ſwallowing up thy good men greedily like a Whale, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring thy goods inſatiably like <hi>Bell,</hi> or rather like hell: but with their tongues they ſpeake nothing but lyes of him, and the cauſe for which he ſuffereth, and yet promoteth for thy peace and freedome.</p>
            <p>Look, look upon him, all yee that paſſe by, yea, ſtand ſtill, (I ſay)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161896:8"/>and look ſteadfaſtly on him, his wife and children; Is it not a wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſpectacle, and are there no teares yet in thine eyes, Whilſt thou beholdeſt it? Looke ſteedily on his bloody ſtripes, terrible gagging, cruell impriſonment, and barbarous uſage, and likewiſe upon his actions and ſufferings ſince; Were theſe unparalleled ſufferings not at all, becauſe moſt of them were ſome yeares, moneths, or weekes agoe?</p>
            <p>Surely, O friends, yee ſeeme (by your practice) to thinke ſo; if it were otherwiſe, whence comes ſo great an alteration in you, though there be both a conſtant and couragious progreſſe in him.</p>
            <p>For no ſooner entred he into any one of his afflictions formerly, but ye flockt about him like ſo many Bees at a hive, like friends and true comforters indeed, ſo that every one thought well or ill of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as they comforted or neglected him.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing yee have found them all as ſtep-mothers that have wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you from him, O then returne, returne, revive in love, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no oppreſſion, nor burthen, nor affliction ſo great, as the neglect of friends to one oppreſſed, burdened, and afflicted for a juſt cauſe, in priſon; Be not you therefore after all the greateſt, but lend him your ſocieties, your comforts, your counſels, and aſſiſtance, as at the firſt, whenevery one was ready to runne, ride, petition, or do any juſt thing for his encouragement, or enlargment.</p>
            <p>And never look that <hi>England</hi> ſhall be free, or that any good is really intended to this Nation, till this worthy man be ſet at liberty, with full reparations for his foule injurious and unjuſt ſufferings; and be ſure ye neither neglect, nor delay your endeavours to effect it, whatever it coſt you, as he accounteth nothing too deare or precious for you; for if any one ſuffer, all ought to ſuffer with him, nor think your ſelves religious either in your Faſts or Feaſts, or any thing elſe, as in uſing all lawfull meanes, which poſsibly may deliver the Captive, and ſet the oppreſſed free. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 586.</p>
            <p>This indeed may coſt you ſomething, for ye are like to go through many difficulties to obtaine it, but for theſe and the like ends, have ye your abilities; and without ayming at ſuch, thinke not your religious exerciſes enough which coſts you little or nothing: O! there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, never ceaſe, till yee procure him either free enlargement with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, or a Legall tryall, that <hi>England</hi> may ceaſe to mourne any more over this weeping ſpectacle.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
